<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Merkle-Trees on VeilChain - Merkle Tree Ledger for Immutable Audit Logs</title><link>https://veilchain.io/tags/merkle-trees/</link><description>Recent content in Merkle-Trees on VeilChain - Merkle Tree Ledger for Immutable Audit Logs</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://veilchain.io/tags/merkle-trees/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>From Blockchain to VeilChain: Getting Bitcoin-Grade Security Without the Overhead</title><link>https://veilchain.io/blog/2024-12-17-blockchain-to-veilchain/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://veilchain.io/blog/2024-12-17-blockchain-to-veilchain/</guid><description>&lt;p>Blockchain promised to revolutionize data integrity. And in many ways, it delivered—Bitcoin&amp;rsquo;s ledger has never been successfully tampered with in over 15 years of operation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But blockchain also brought massive overhead: consensus mechanisms, gas fees, scaling limitations, and operational complexity. For most applications that need data integrity, this overhead is overkill.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>VeilChain strips away the unnecessary parts of blockchain while keeping what matters: cryptographic immutability. Here&amp;rsquo;s how we deliver Bitcoin-grade security without the blockchain baggage.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Why Merkle Trees Are the Gold Standard for Data Integrity</title><link>https://veilchain.io/blog/2024-12-15-why-merkle-trees/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://veilchain.io/blog/2024-12-15-why-merkle-trees/</guid><description>&lt;p>When Ralph Merkle patented his namesake tree structure in 1979, he couldn&amp;rsquo;t have predicted that it would become the backbone of Bitcoin, Git, Certificate Transparency, and countless other systems that require verifiable data integrity. Today, Merkle trees are the gold standard for proving that data hasn&amp;rsquo;t been tampered with—and for good reason.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-a-merkle-tree">What Is a Merkle Tree?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A Merkle tree is a hash-based data structure that allows efficient and secure verification of large data sets. Think of it as a cryptographic receipt for your data that makes tampering immediately detectable.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Merkle Tree Ledger for Tamper-Proof Audit Logs | VeilChain</title><link>https://veilchain.io/blog/2024-12-14-introducing-veilchain/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://veilchain.io/blog/2024-12-14-introducing-veilchain/</guid><description>&lt;p>We&amp;rsquo;re excited to announce the launch of VeilChain, an open-source merkle tree ledger service designed to bring Bitcoin-grade data immutability to your applications. VeilChain provides tamper-proof audit logs and cryptographic data integrity without the overhead of running a full blockchain.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-problem-data-integrity-without-blockchain">The Problem: Data Integrity Without Blockchain&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Modern applications need verifiable data integrity. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re building immutable audit logs for compliance, document notarization systems, or supply chain tracking, you need cryptographic proof that data hasn&amp;rsquo;t been tampered with.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>